<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>Devang Sampat</title>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/"/>
 <updated>2020-11-30T19:55:33-08:00</updated>
 <id>http://localhost:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name>Devang Sampat</name>
 </author>
 
 
 <entry>
   <title>Early Retirement 401K Investing</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/401k"/>
   <updated>2013-07-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/posts/401k</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;motivation-behind-investing-in-a-401k&quot;&gt;Motivation behind investing in a 401K&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having started a new job, and being thrown in the depths of all that is the adult world,
one thing I learnt about is retirement savings primarily through 401Ks and Roth IRAs.
Contributions to a 401K are tax deferred which is just a fancy way of saying that instead
of paying taxes on it now, you pay taxes on it when you withdraw the money. This is great
if you know you’ll be in a lower tax bracket when you retire. It means that instead of 
earning $1 now, giving 30 cents in taxes, and investing the remaining 70 cents. You can
invest the full $1 right now, and then pay 15 or 20 cents tax when you’re 65.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;downside-to-401k&quot;&gt;Downside to 401K&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, there is a catch to this. Any withdrawals you make from a 401K before the 
age of 55 incur a 10% penalty fee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-loophole&quot;&gt;The loophole&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you want to retire earlier than 55, or you need some of the cash in your 401K
for whatever reason. One option is to just withdraw the cash now and take the 10% hit. If
your employer matches your 401K contribution, this might seem like a great idea because
for the $1 you contributed, you still got $1.90 back. If you know you’re going to need
this cash though, with a little bit of planning you can get the full $2. The way to do 
this is to roll over the 401K into a Roth IRA. You will pay full taxes on whatever you
rollover based on your current tax bracket. The advantage, is that you can withdraw the
principal from a Roth IRA after 5 years. Withdrawing the principal means you can only
withdraw what you put in at the time, not any interest you may have gained on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;comparison-with-other-approaches&quot;&gt;Comparison with other approaches&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To clarify with an example, let’s say you contributed $1 to your 401K, and your employer 
matched 100% of it for a total of $2 in your 401K. Let’s say you left it there for 2
years with an interest rate of 8%, so at the end of 2 years, you have a total of $2.33 in
your 401K. Now you roll that over to a 401K, and let’s say you pay 15% tax on it. So
your total rollover amount is $1.9805. After 5 years, with 8% interest, your Roth IRA
will have a total of $2.91, of which you can withdraw $1.9805 leaving a total of $0.9295
in your Roth IRA. If you’d left it all in your 401K, you’d have $3.43 in the account, and
if we assume you were 55 and withdrew it at a 15% tax rate, then you’d have $2.9155 in 
hand which is slightly more(or significantly more depending on the number of zeros in
your real investment) than the rollover approach. If you had more years to retirement,
your investment would also grow more with the full 401K approach, so if you know that
you won’t need the cash until 55, then that approach is probably better for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say in comparison you tried to invest your $1 the regular way. So you paid taxes
on it based on your current tax bracket of 25%. So you have $0.75 left, and invested it
for the 7 years with an 8% tax rate, that will result in a total of $1.29.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that this does require you to be in the lower tax bracket at the time of rollover,
which is 5 years before you can see the money, so it requires some planning on your part,
and won’t work for an emergency situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why not just invest in a Roth IRA to begin with? Well for one you pay taxes on your $1 
right now. The yearly contribution limit is also only $5000 in comparison to the $17,500
of the 401K.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Results From Blocking The Newsfeed</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/results-from-blocking-the-newsfeed"/>
   <updated>2013-07-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/posts/results-from-blocking-the-newsfeed</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;About a month ago, I posted about how to block the Facebook newsfeed. As a result of doing so I noticed some changes in my life - some obvious, and some not so obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;productivity&quot;&gt;Productivity&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The single biggest change, which many will anticipate, is that I got a lot more done. Even
though I spent a fair bit of time staring at the blank newsfeed waiting for a notification
update, I still spent less overall time on Facebook. It also had the unintended effect of
causing me to realize how little interest I actually had in such things, as well as in 
things such a Reddit which led to an overall reduction in mindless internet distractions. 
My personal interpretation of still wanting to stare at the blank newsfeed is to reduce
it to something like an email. Email is like a game where the brain rewards us with 
dopamine for viewing a new email/notification. I am not a cognitive scientist by any means
but here is an interesting &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lsa.umich.edu/psych/research&amp;amp;labs/berridge/publications/Berridge&amp;amp;RobinsonBrResRev1998.pdf&quot;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;interpersonal&quot;&gt;Interpersonal&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also felt more disconnected with friends lives, so instead of just browsing through the
feed, I messaged more of them which meant I had fewer interactions overall, but
many more high quality interactions. However, this meant I also probably annoyed quite a 
few friends by sharing one too many trivial life occurences and facepalm-worthy joke.
It did present an interesting opportunity to pose the same story to multiple people and 
see how they reacted to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, I also experienced less of what I would like to call ‘Friday Night Jealousy’.
This jealously feeling that whatever activity you are pursuing on your Friday Night, 
regardless of how social or exciting it is, is nowhere as great as what the people on your
Facebook feed appear to me doing right now. Ironically, since I had so much more free time,
instead of normally just looking at what others are doing and feeling a sense of melanchoy,
I ended up so bored that I actively tried to find things to do which resulted in getting
some great new stories such as a crackhead trying to get into our house during a party. 
Stories which I could then pose to multiple people as mentioned above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;miscellaneous&quot;&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also seems that some of these behaviours have continued despite my recent reactivation 
of Facebook such as reduced Facebook usage overall, and a preference for messaging over
more public interactions. Some behaviours have returned to their old ways though such as
occasional, but not as frequent pointless scrolls through the newfeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from these behaviours, I also noticed that this negatively affected my Klout score.
It decreased from around 61 to around 56, and is now at 52.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Blocking The Facebook Newsfeed</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/hiding-the-facebook-newsfeed"/>
   <updated>2013-06-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/posts/hiding-the-facebook-newsfeed</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-i-did-it&quot;&gt;Why I Did It&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I often find myself wanting to check my Facebook to see if I have any new messages or notifications. Regardless of their existence, I always end up wasting a significant amount of time simply scrolling through my news feed, every so often stopping at an item of interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This adds no real value to my daily life because one of my friends will always inadvertently notify me in some form or the other about important updates in my friends’ lives. The other updates are mere distractions that allow me to spend less time getting work done. As a result, I wanted to be able to block the news feed, but still access messages, notifications, and of course be able to specifically go to a friends page who I want to see updates for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-to-do-it&quot;&gt;How To Do It&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did this by blocking the DIVs for Facebook by marking them as ads in &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/adblock/gighmmpiobklfepjocnamgkkbiglidom&quot;&gt;AdBlock&lt;/a&gt;. You can add the DIVs by right-clicking on the AdBlock icon -&amp;gt; Options -&amp;gt; Customize -&amp;gt; Manually Edit Filters.  Then add the following line:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;www.facebook.com##DIV[id=”pagelet_home_stream”]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also added the following lines to block the left and right side pane, because I thought it cluttered up the interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;www.facebook.com##DIV[id=”sideNav”][class=”uiFutureSideNav”]
www.facebook.com##DIV[id=”pagelet_ego_pane_w”]
www.facebook.com##DIV[id=”sideNav”][class=”uiFutureSideNav uiNarrowSideNav”]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result looks something like this: &lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/TydXWMZ.png?1&quot; alt=&quot;Imgur&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>When Duck Typing Goes Wrong</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/when-duck-typing-goes-wrong"/>
   <updated>2013-05-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/posts/when-duck-typing-goes-wrong</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-do-we-want&quot;&gt;What Do We Want&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Duck typing is the idea looking at the object
based on its properties such as the types of the variables and methods it
contains, instead of looking at an object based on what class it inherits from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-do-we-want-it&quot;&gt;Why Do We Want It&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s an example in Scala to demonstrate this, though it should be noted 
that technically Scala has &lt;em&gt;Structural Typing&lt;/em&gt; which is a more robust version 
of duck typing, but the principle is the same. This should print out 
“I am a man” if a Male is passed in, and “I am a woman” if a Female is 
passed in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;object Male {
	def speak(value: String) = {
      &quot;I am a man&quot;
    }
}

object Female {
	def speak(value: String) = {
	  &quot;I am a woman&quot;
	}
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we can define a method makeThemTalk that will accept anything that
matches the description above:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;def makeThemTalk(human: {def speak(value: String): String}) {
    println(human.speak())
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several reasons why this is helpful - for one the code is cleaner,
and more importantly, we can now pass in any object that has a speak method
which takes in a String, and returns a String. There’s no need to keep track
of allowable object types nor is there a need to take an object oriented
approach by making each object inherit from some superclass and then 
checking for the existence of such a relationship. This can quickly become
dangerous however if one is not careful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-we-shouldnt-want-it&quot;&gt;Why We Shouldn’t Want It&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s say I’m working on some software that allows the police to arrest someone
with the click of a button. So I write an object and method like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;object BadGuy {
  private var name = &quot;Danny Ocean&quot;
  def getName() = {
    name
  }
}

def arrest(person: { def getName(): String}) {
  findAndTerminate(person)
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems all fine and dandy, and indeed it works, but we must be careful.
Let’s say we wanted to expand our application so that we could look up
the information for regular people as well. So we write:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;object GoodGuy {
  private var name = &quot;Danny Doogooder&quot;
  def getName() = {
    name
  }
}

def getProfile(person: { def getName(): String}) {
  findProfile(person)
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem here is that from the viewpoint of the arrest method, GoodGuy and
BadGuy are structually equivalent. This means that it is just as easy to pass
in a GoodGuy object to arrest, as it is to pass in a BadGuy. Using duck typing
does away with the clear separation between objects that you get with using
something like inheritance. As a result, it is easy to make a mistake like
the above which can result in potential security issues by being able to
pass objects to methods that you really do not want to be able to pass in.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>What Programmers Can Learn From Pathological Gamblers</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/what-programmers-can-learn-from-pathological-gamblers"/>
   <updated>2013-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/posts/what-programmers-can-learn-from-pathological-gamblers</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Think about how many times you’ve thought you were so close to something, that if you just kept at it for a little longer, then you’d finally succeed. 
&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/CPjsGaU.png&quot; alt=&quot;Imgur&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others take the opposite approach. They belive that by continuing at the task, they could make things worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/GHgeCWj.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Imgur&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do we know when to keep working, and when to call it a day?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-near-miss-effect&quot;&gt;The Near Miss Effect&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two years ago, researchers at the Southern Illnois University published a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2861872/&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; in which they ran an experiment on two groups of people: those who were pathlogical gamblers, and those who gambled, but not compulsively). The experiment simulated a slot machine which had three outcomes - win, near miss, and loss. A near miss is when the slots mostly matched, except for one column. They found that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pathological gamblers were more excited about winning than nonpathological gamblers even when there was no actual monetary reward for a win&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Neurologically, pathlogical gamblers saw near misses as wins, while nonpathological gamblers saw near misses as losses&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now in gambling, a near miss is in reality a loss. However, if we translate these results into a different field, then near misses might actually be very useful!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-pathological-programmer&quot;&gt;The Pathological Programmer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you are now Joe Code Monkey. Instead of having an addiction to gambling, Joe  has somehow trained himself to have an addiction to writing software. His boss wants him to write The Next Big Thing for the company. So he starts by figuring out what features are needed, then he writes all your tests(woohoo TDD!), and now he needs to write the actual software. For the purposes of this example, we can simulate a slot machine here by saying that for every feature he writes and runs against the test bench, he will get one of three results:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All the tests pass&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Almost all tests pass&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All tests fail&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having become a pathological programmer, Joe get ones of those rushes that makes the hair on the back of his neck stand up not only when he finally has a 100% working feature, but he also when he ran a 80% working feature. This means that instead of calling it a day because he felt that he achieved nothing today, he keeps going and gets the entire feature done. What would previously have been an quite familiar 2am existental crisis, is now a source of inspiration to push forward!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-downside&quot;&gt;The Downside&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, just like with being a pathological gambler, there can be harmful consequences to one’s personal life. Is spending all your time and money on your work really much better than spending all your time and money on gambling? Success may mean that your boss likes you and gives you a big raise, and of course there’s the dopamine hit, but winning also means you get a lot of money and a dopamine hit.  There is a risk of becoming a workaholic, of health concerns, of losing friends and family, all for nothing. Instead of giving you a raise, your boss might do the worst thing possible by &lt;strong&gt;NOT&lt;/strong&gt; firing you - meaning that you have yet another day to come back, to play the slot machine.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>
